Guide to the American Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection OH.008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection
1985-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Teachers. United Action Caucus
American Federation of Teachers. Local 3882 (Clerical Union)
Filardo, Anne Levine, 1922-2010
Loane, Scott
Wheeler, Joyce
OH.008
2.4 Linear Feet in 1 cassette box, 1 half manuscript box, 6 items in a shared card box, and 22 disks in a shared CD box.
63 audiocassettes
The American Federation of Teachers (AFT) is the second largest national teachers union in the United States and was founded by Margaret Haley in Chicago, Illinois in 1916. As of 2021, its members include pre-K through 12th grade teachers; paraprofessionals and school-related personnel; government employees at local, state, and federal levels; college and university faculty and staff, and nurses and other healthcare professionals. The American Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection consists of audio recordings and transcripts of interviews with American Federation of Teachers (AFT) members, staff people, and officers, with a concentration on union activities in the 1950s and 1960s. The interviews were conducted between 1985 and 1987, and topics include the role of women in the AFT, the Civil Rights movement and minority members within the AFT, opinions of past and present union leaders, the 1960 merger of New York City locals, and the Progressive Caucus.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Scott Loane on behalf of the American Federation of Teachers, Local 3882 in 1997; additional materials were donated by Anne Filardo and Peter Filardo in 1997. Some materials were found in the repository and added to the collection, there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.054, 1997.055, 1997.056, 1997.057, 1997.058, and 2009.031.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by the narrator's last name.
Historical Note
The American Federation of Teachers (AFT) is the second largest national teachers union in the United States and was founded by Margaret Haley in Chicago, Illinois in 1916. Haley served as the first national organizer and Charles Stillman as the first president. Over the first four years of the AFT it claimed 174 locals and approximately 9,000 members. During the 1930s membership increased in urban areas along with general labor union growth in cities and the AFT successfully lobbied for teacher tenure laws in 17 states. After investigations of Communist infiltration and influence in some locals, the AFT expelled two New York City locals and the Philadelphia union in 1941. One of the New York locals went on to become the New York City Teachers Union. During World War II, AFT locals in some cities won contracts through collective bargaining. The AFT continued to emphasize the need for collective bargaining in the postwar period and locals began to strike for better wages in contract, with the St. Paul, Minnesota the first local to strike, in 1946. In the 1950s, teacher discontent increased as wages in private employment continued to outpace teacher salaries and the battle for collective bargaining in education began in New York City. Albert Shanker and David Selden brought about a merger of the fragmented New York locals in 1960 under the title of United Federation of Teachers within the AFT. In 1960, the UFT won bargaining rights, and after a short strike in 1962, concluded a contract with the New York City Board of Education. The UFT victory in New York moved it into a dominant position within the AFT. In 1963 the AFT national convention repealed its no-strike policy. Attempts to effect a national merger of the AFT and the National Education Association (NEA) collapsed in the late 1990s. In 2017, the AFT included over one million members in major cities across the United States. As of 2021, its members include pre-K through 12th grade teachers; paraprofessionals and school-related personnel; government employees at local, state, and federal levels; college and university faculty and staff, and nurses and other healthcare professionals.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access CDs for some audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Other audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The American Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection consists of audio recordings of interviews with American Federation of Teachers (AFT) members, staff people, and officers, with a concentration on union activities in the 1950s and 1960s. The interviews were conducted between 1985 and 1987 with members who were active throughout the United States, but most interviews focus on activities in New York, New York; Michigan; Chicago, Illinois; and East Coast cities. Topics include the role of women in the AFT, the Civil Rights movement and minority members within the AFT, opinions of past and present union leaders, the 1960 merger of New York City locals, and the Progressive Caucus. Narrators include David Elsila, editor of The American Teacher, and David Selden, past president of the AFT. Index summaries or transcripts exist for all the interviews, with the exception of Carl Megel, Fred Nauman, and Rebecca Simonson.
Teachers' unions -- Officials and employees -- United States -- Interviews.; Collective bargaining -- Teachers -- United States.; Audiocassettes.; Strikes and lockouts -- Teachers; Women labor union members -- United States.; Minority labor union members.; Filardo, Anne Levine, 1922-2010; Loane, Scott; American Federation of Teachers. Local 3882 (Clerical Union); Wheeler, Joyce; Selden, David; Elsila, Dave; United Federation of Teachers
- Rose Claffey, 1986-08-10-1987-04-10
  Scope and Contents
  Unionism in 40s, AFT in 50s-70s, Selden's and Shanker's presidencies.
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 1A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Charles Cogen, 1986-07-25-1986-10-24
  Sam Gompers; Counts', Selden's, and Megel's presidencies, NYC 1960-1964, organizing as president, strike debate.
  Transcript available.
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 2A-B)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd OH_008_ref3_000001 -- _000004)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Patrick Daly, 1987-04-04
  Dearborn Federation 1955-1987, civil rights movement, AFT presidencies.
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 3A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
- David Elsila, 1987-04-06
  The American Teacher.
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 4A-B)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
- John Madison Fewkes, 1986-07-30-1986-07-31
  Chicago Teachers Union, presidency, AFT 1940s-1960s
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 5A-B)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Catherine McGourty, 1987-03-17
  Secretary for AFT in Chicago, Megel's presidency
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 7A-B)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Carl Megel, 1986-08-26-1986-10-10
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 6A-E)
- Fred Nauman, undated
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 8A-C)
- Robert Porter, 1986-11-19
  Collective bargaining in local 1220, AFT and caucus politics, Cogen, merger
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 9A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mary Ellen Riordan, 1987-04-05
  Detroit Federation of Teachers, presidency 1960s-80s, Selden, caucus
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 10A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Herrick Roth, 1987-02-16
  AFT collective bargaining, AFL-CIO
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 11A-D)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 9)
- David Selden, 1987-01-04-1987-01-22
  The Elders in MI, Dearborn Federation of Teachers, organizing, Teachers' Guild, Teacher Militancy, collective bargain, caucus system, presidency
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 12A-C, Box Shared Tamiment 092, Cassette 12D-E)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd OH_008_ref3_000001 -- _000010)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 10)
- William Simons, 1986-11-18-1986-11-20
  WWII, Black teachers, local, integration, collective bargaining, VP, merger
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 092, Cassette 13A-D)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd OH_008_ref3_000001 -- _000008)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Rebecca Simonson, 1985-06-29-1985-06-30
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 092, Cassette 14A-C)
- Charles and Mary Smith, 1987-03-18
  Texas union formation, Charles' presidency, 1963 strike, AFT in 1960s
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 092, Cassette 15A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Raoul Teilhet, 1986-09-10
  Pasadena union organization, collective bargaining, caucus, merger, the NEA
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 092, Cassette 16A-C)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)